my concern is a
tutorial is of course my daily practice
you told it many times so
i should
during the day i should
just apart than that
apart than that
my
routine meditation in the morning just
being aware of
breath and then the periphery body
where the breath depends on
so this is the summary of this should be
the summary of my meditation now that
i'm in my practice
now that i am uh
going to base so i would like to have a
kind of summary for that
or a guidance maybe in the sense of what
to do yeah
i mean i saw here uh for uh two or three
weeks but
like a summary for the
what do you think
or you can
be aware of your body
you can be aware of your breath or your
body but why are you doing that
my ultimate ultimate goal is to get to
right field of course
and
just trying not to do things out of uh
desire and diversion and illusion
that would be the
so how are those things done can you can you
accidentally
unintentionally do things out of greed
aversion and delusion
no they come up and uh then i shouldn't
react uh to that greed
which is coming up which is uh
just not sure that react would be the
best description it's not about reaction
see reaction is oh i just reacted
somebody scares you you react
you can't prevent that
and well act act and react is different
well act act and react is different
exactly so that's my point can those
things happen by accident
they can't
so greed aversion delusion cannot
accidentally occur
when i forgot or something they're
always on the level of your choice
so they're always chosen
that means i choose to act out of grief yeah
means i choose to act out of grief yeah
yeah
you do on some level you do you have to
be doing
and that's the point like people the
only way to start recognizing such
choices is to start
looking at choices per se
in general
but people think like oh i haven't i
acted out of great diversion delusion
because i wasn't focused enough or
concentrated or calm enough no you acted
because you chose to act
so the only way to get closer
to that recognition when you choose to
act out of these things is to keep
pondering on the motivation behind your
actions intentions and choices you make
throughout the day
yes as i said being calm is is nice it's
fine and you can calm down sure but that
has nothing to do with your choices
but if you think that
a great diversion delusion comes out of
you know accidental non-calmness or
slip of the mind or something if they
don't no they came because when you
chose them you chose to allow them to
enter that's it
so that's what you need to look for the
problem
then on top of that if calming helps you
reflect further on your choices yes
that's fine
but you have to abandon the view that
calming will make me choose better no it
won't value of certain choices
value of certain choices
and value against certain other choices
pondering on those values and importance
and danger and peril that will help you
choose better
and that peril will not be seen on
itself by itself and it will not come as
a result of you know watching the
nostrils it will come if you make the
effort to see it and think about it and
remind yourself of everything that the
buddha said
and this reminding is also of course an
issue for me i mean it is
that's really where the practice is like
bhavana as in keep it in the being
yeah maintain it a certain context that
you need to be
uh
knowing be
aware of it and clarifying it further
so bhavana is not on the level of
calming calming until the experience of
the pleasant kind comes over and then i
don't even think about greed aversion
and delusion
yeah that was never the problem the
problem is could you think about greed
aversion delusion and the answer is yes
because the danger has not been
cultivated enough seen enough understood
enough so you can do all the calming you want
so you can do all the calming you want
the moment that calming goes away
you you don't know where the problem is
the problem was you are still
unwittingly yet intentionally
uh choosing great diversion delusion on
body speed on the level of body speech
or mind
and that's
what it's saying to me as well is if you
are watching your intentions
your choices that you're making
and valuing the right choices and
devaluing the wrong ones
then you are automatically or by default
what starts to happen is you are aware
of
your body what you are physically doing
you know why am i doing this so you are
aware of your physical actions
you're aware of what you're saying
you're aware of your mind
this comes out of it you don't have to
be aware of the body hoping that you're
going to
know why you're going why you are doing
things because you're watching your
knees you're watching your abdomen rise
and fall
and that's going to reveal why you're
doing something you have to ask yourself
why am i doing this yeah
yeah
and that's really what mindfulness is if
you want a method for mindfulness it's
that question that results in
mindfulness not
not
sensation watching or belly bhavan or
whatever else people do it's like you do
that expecting experience oh no why am i
doing what i'm doing see that question
already puts you in a state of
mindfulness and then if you keep pushing further
and then if you keep pushing further
with such questioning you will arrive at
certain universal truths such as oh
whatever i'm doing is in order to avoid
pain prolonged pleasure
choices i make no matter how subtle of
course they always have to be rooted in
in those three principles greed aversion
delusion or non-greed non-aversion
non-delusion and that's where the problem is and
and that's where the problem is and
that's what a solution is
the issue is that during the day for
example suddenly i get i become aware that uh
suddenly i get i become aware that uh
i'm thinking about
uh a unpleasant thought for example
i'm angry about something
that's the place where i should uh then
practice or that well yeah yeah because
because like the whole point is to
recognize that the practice is on the
level of that liability to angry
thoughts or lustful thoughts not the
actual one sure actual one but that's
already too late okay so if it's
actual anger or last year you've got to
restrain it not act out of it but then
when it's not there you shouldn't start
thinking oh okay i dealt with the
problem no no as the buddha would often
say a monk would review his mind and ask
himself can honorism unwholesome things
arise in this mind
and then oh yes and now you start
cultivating that god the danger if such
things arise
how would they arise through what
choices you make little thing here a
little thing there before you know it
mind is filled with lust and you're
accepting it
but it's always on that level of
welcoming delighting entertaining
engaging with mentally and that is a
matter of choice
now of course if somebody is not
restrained in the body
uh you know these subtle choices on the
level of their thoughts will not be seen
but nevertheless they are choices they
are things you choose to
um allow so to speak in the sense of
have a have a welcoming attitude towards
that's why you have to really like
hammer in that sense of danger so that
you uproot the attitude of this is nice
this is good this is friendly this is
for me
but you you would arrive at that
you you would arrive at that
yeah if you spend obviously if you keep
the precepts god descends those
and then throughout the day whatever
you're doing
ask yourself questions endure doubt if
it's unclear
but fundamentally recognize that
whatever you choose to do on the level
of body speech your mind cannot happen
accidentally it's always
on the level of your choice thus
at the same time see it feels like oh
this is so
overwhelming but at the same time it's
actually easier it becomes easier
because you realize okay so i don't need
to worry about these things accidentally
happening affecting me oppressing me and
now i have to deal with them on and on
because they just accidentally came in
that becomes impossible
so the clearer you become in in sort of
this type of balance this type of
cultivation the more confident you are
because you know no no doesn't matter
what circumstances are coming this way
good or bad i'm the one who opens the
door and the clearer you are with that the
and the clearer you are with that the
clearer the door becomes and the more
confident and safe you feel because you
won't open the door once you know the
danger but if you keep perpetrating the
view that these disturbances of the mind
happen accidentally because you were not
concentrated enough or calm enough
you keep a patriot in the view that the
problem comes on its from outside on its
own and you have nothing to do with it
you just have to deal with it and uh and
that's not the case
and then you will always feel undermined
by it doesn't matter how how well your
concentration is developed and
commitment to practice you're always
going to feel undermined because you you
undermine yourself by putting it
externally whatever happens if it's if it's sort of
whatever happens if it's if it's sort of
unpleasant
you won't know where the problem was and
you would think it was because of the
circumstances and then you would try to
double down in your calmness and
concentration and ignoring and covering
up so that these things don't arise but
they were never the problem
the problem was your intentional choice
ignorant one lustful one or angry one
that's it
so if there is an anger in your mind
thoughts came up yeah you didn't ask for
it
but you have a choice now am i trying to get
you have a choice now am i trying to get
rid of this
acting out of anger
am i acting out of anger further towards
what i you know
projected as the reason of my anger or
am i able to just endure it
you know let the mind kick and scream
but not not engage with such thoughts
not try to you know get rid of them
because you can't but you can certainly
not welcome them so no you can you can
be there in front of the door shout and
scream but you are not welcome inside
so your attitude of no welcoming that's
the line that's what you need to develop
but not further and not less than that
and the only way you can develop that
and develop clarity in regard for that
attitude is
keep looking for it keep asking
questions keep reviewing it won't happen magically
keep reviewing it won't happen magically
on account of a concentration experience
or something it's just impossible
that instruction that the
two factors for the rising of right view
being the the instruction from another
the word of another
and johannes
which is like being able to to know your
intentions behind your actions right
well knowing the origin of your actions so
knowing the origin of your actions so
having the instruction and then watching
what are you doing
yeah yeah see where it's rooted
and but what's the
but what's the
what's usually the problem with that
with the honest woman the cicada
the the the view the
the common view
yeah so say like like you described this
to somebody
knowing the origin of your intentions of
your choices
why people can't see that why
why would that require
so much explanation as it does and
people would still do it wrongly
what's the
where's the issue
well because you're so absorbed in your
sense sense world senses
sense world senses
unrestrained
never have any self-reflection never pause
have any self-reflection never pause
just you're just going with whatever
feels good avoiding whatever feels bad
so how can you see your mind how can you
step back to see
your intentions
yeah but like even the person if they're
not restrained
and when you tell them about yoni
sumanesikara the origin of your
intentions they can get their head
around but why
but why
that whatever they get their head around
why that will not be yoni sumanesikar
why that will not be the origin
it will be abstract
sure why why would it be abstract
so let's just stick with the origin of
your action yeah so
needs to be
attended properly let's say like that
and when people think if people have not
been sense restrained
uh guarded of the sense those
when they think they're attending it
properly they're not why
well they're turning it into an object
exactly that's exactly the point
they basically attend to it as another
object of their senses even thoughts
and that's not what it is
so they cannot
see anything um
[Music] more refined than object of what i'm
more refined than object of what i'm
attending
because that's what the mind is mind
takes that as a threshold of what is
and mind takes that as a threshold of
what is because the lack of the sense
restraint and when i say lack of virtue
and sense restraint i mean properly done
properly in other words
in other words
endured properly sufficiently because
it's easy for people to be virtuous when
they adopt the external set of
circumstances tradition
uh community and so on then you just
stick to the external behavior but you
haven't taken on the virtue
that's why the factor of silabata
paramasa is one of the first three to go
if you start doing things rightly
so if you have taken it on in a sense of
you are enduring doubt you are still
questioning uh the intentions behind
your action you don't just not do or do
because the rules or the tradition says
so
so if things are on the right level then
yes your mind will cease to maintain the
notion that the only thing that is real
the only thing that exists is the one
that i can attend to or access through
my senses
so yoni so meaning boom manatee karmic
the origin of your attention
so whatever you choose to attend i
direct your attention to words
the only soviet is at the back of it
so that's where this attention is coming
from and you cannot attend that
in the same sense as you said before
and i cannot see itself
it's just impossible yet the knowledge
that the eye is there as a prerequisite
for seeing can be developed as a present
absence exactly it is simultaneously present but
exactly it is simultaneously present but
it can never be directly
uh
present as an object of your attention
yet it is present as a basis for your
attention and that's that subtlety that
and that's that subtlety that
again you can reason and you can uh
abstract it and you can get your head
around it but unless the mind has been
developed through uh correct endurance
first it will be just another thing you attend
it will be just another thing you attend
to
so it won't be the yoni saw of your mana
sikhara so to kind of describe
so to kind of describe
that in a in a practical way in a way
which isn't abstract one could say it's
like an absence of
greed aversion and distraction this this
present absence
in the sense that uh
by not conceiving
this this
um mind or
not turning it into an object in front
of me one is is seeing that it's arisen
by itself yes but like a see
not turning into an object
can become your object yes that thought
becomes your object now
so you cannot just
make a choice to attend to it
you can recognize what is a necessary
basis for developing recognition of such
attention yeah and the necessary basis
would be taking on the virtue rightly
sensory strain rightly and doing it on
the right level
and the best example would be uh like
you know the the unpleasant state of
doubt just generally what how do you go about
just generally what how do you go about
it
in your doubtful whether doubtful about
rules or precepts or how do you go about
it do you take it for granted that you
must get rid of it or are you able to
endure it without acting out of it
and during it without acting out of it
is closer to to yoni sumanesikara
then you're pondering about yoni
sumasikara having acted out of doubt
plus they are putting not just yourself
putting your entire existence in in
question because it is always in
question the impermanence is one giant question
the impermanence is one giant question
mark that undermines you
and doubt exemplifies that that's why
doubt is so unpleasant and people always
try to get rid of it even if it's
externally not that significant
the experience of doubt
is always like
cannot be tolerated cannot be endured
because as i said it exemplifies that
underlying condition
condition
of being undermined by things that are
not in your control that are uncertain
so if you're able to endure things on
that level
not act out i not break precepts but not
give in to overly defining either in
order to get rid of the doubt yeah see
you are seeing the origins now of what
you're attending and why you're
attending but the only reason you're seeing and
but the only reason you're seeing and
you're getting to know them is because
you're enduring them you can't just
choose to attend them
yeah so john is the result of correctly
so john is the result of correctly
developing your mind because you could
choose to develop to to attend to
everything you said with craving exactly
becomes an object of attention that
becomes affected with craving
so yeah that's an interesting way to put
doubt you know doubt is
that exemplifies your existence
the big question mark
shows you the nature of
this what's happening your situation
and then you're trying to solve it
you're running about trying to solve
that there's anxiety there complexity
there's anxiety there complexity
what should i do how should i do it
where should i go what you know
so doubt there's so doubts
why is doubt a hindrance
yeah it's a good question
isn't it anybody has a thought on that
why is that a hindrance
um because it entails
uh being moved without
it entails losing perspective on
the nature of
one's experience um
by by
well for example you said the the idea
of trying to solve
this uncertainty
yeah one can only why why would one try
to solve the uncertainty
where would those acts be rooted in
sorry aversion
pain yeah aversion to pain
that's it
so doubt is a hindrance because you want
to get rid of the pain of it
so doubt hinders you
because you take for granted your
aversion to discomfort
you act out of it
in the same sense centrality is a
hindrance because you take for granted
your your delight in comfort
your delight in comfort
pleasure
that's why you hinder it it doesn't
hinder you by itself that's the whole
point you're responsible for being hindered
you're responsible for being hindered
now the talent is not necessarily it
doesn't have to be a hindrance no no
it's just putting things in question
but the thing is see putting things in
question does not necessarily need to
cause you existential pain
but if it does cause you essential pain
um
to that extent it's a hindrance because
to that extent you're still resisting
the pain
but what would be a difference between
doubt as a feta and as a hindrance
so the fatter of doubt
kind of on the level of what we just
said that taking on the virtues on on
account of external authority
doubt as a
as a as a feta is on the same level
which of course it is because it
pertains to the same thing
because there's choice involved in the
hindrance the fetter is something which
is a result of uh
this is just a lack of
prior um discernment
um discernment
whereas the hindrance is something which
you're actively engaging with
no
no no
fatter is something obviously actively
maintained
that fatal doubt is bound up with the
other two
first fetters their personality view
and you know wrongly holding the virtues and
you know wrongly holding the virtues and
the duties
and the habits and the practice
and the whole business of personality view
the whole business of personality view
voted in this assumption
i am i exist this is myself
that can never be fully and totally
clarified and and made certain because
and and made certain because
you exist within a situation always and
so you cannot step outside of that
outside of your experience in order to
gain a definition for yourself exactly so the
a definition for yourself exactly so the
whole business of existence
is is by definition ambiguous and
therefore uncertain this is why the
second factor after personality view is
precisely doubt
and then it seems to me that in order to
deal with this doubt when it's done
wrongly one is going to grasp after
external patterns already set up whether
it is daily routines
32 precepts and all the rest of it
and then one just keeps going around in
circles and circles one personality view
is seen as it is
then there is this timelessness of
dhamma with it so the whole point of i
have to do this in order to get that i
have some insight or some calm or
freedom from doubt this sort of
time interference which which sits there
keeps reinforcing the doubt because you
do something now hoping for results in
the future but you will never be quite
clear whether what you're doing is right
it needs to be seen
basically um
um
in a more direct sense
yeah it's just so that's the but why why
that's all fine but why would that doubt
why is it a fetter still
see somebody who is free from a feather
of doubt their existence is still in the
same question it hasn't been resolved
sotapanna still has plenty of work to do
yes but he's free from the fettering
aspect of that doubt
what is the fettering aspect of the
doubt as a fatter
well when personality view or assumption of
when personality view or assumption of
self is seen as impermanent
which is the case for the sotapana then
with that that feather of doubt wanting
to make your existence certain and
having stability there this is what i am
this is myself and i want to fix that
forever that whole attempt is finished because
that whole attempt is finished because
the impermanence of that underlying
assumption of self-esteem
so doubt doesn't better him anymore
because the whole notion of him or her
is sort of
comes and goes now so what happens then
when doubt is present for him
for such person what's the difference
between so doubt is present for somebody who is
so doubt is present for somebody who is
not free from the fettering aspect of
doubt yes and then doubt is present for
somebody who is free from the fettering
aspect of doubt what's the practical
difference between two of them
well for somebody who is not free from
the feather of doubt in the sense that
hindmans might be fueling all those
lower feathers still
but when the fetus are out of the way
those hindustans are actually being more
properly seen for the first time as
hinderances
yeah but that's again taking one but
between the two what's the difference
just in terms of doubt
between the one who is fatted by the
doubt and the one who isn't both
experiencing doubt one is fatter by the
experience of that the other one isn't
yes where is the precise difference between
where is the precise difference between
the two examples well the precise
difference is that the fetter of doubts
is the result of not seeing dhamma but
someone who sees dharma doesn't have
that doubt so he might still be due to
sure sensuality and the other hidden yes
he's just that's again that the answer
is on the level of why he's not fatted
oh he's not fatter because he sees the
dhamma right we cover that okay but
what's the difference
between the one who has seen the dharma
and it's not fatter by the doubt that is
present and another one who is flattered
by the doubt it's present presence in
the dharma
not why but what is the difference
between the two
practically exemplified which is exactly
back into the question
why that doubt how or rather what is the
factor of the fatter of the doubt what
is the fattering aspect
that would be the difference between the
two
the way they go about it
gone stay more one tries to deal with it
and the other recognizes it and where is
where would that be rooted in the
version sorry aversion aversion to pain yeah
sorry aversion aversion to pain yeah
overall it would be rooted basically in
a view so he still puts the one that is
fettered by the presence of doubt takes
for granted and that's the assumption
that's the view that's why it's a fatter
takes for granted that getting rid of
doubt must be done uh should be welcomed
must be done uh should be welcomed
it's uh it's his duty to do so to
clarify it in other words he has all
these views or a view a wrong view that
justifies dealing with the doubt
while in reality all he justifies is
aversion to its pain acting towards
getting rid of the discomfort
and that's why that is rooted in taking
yourself for granted i the atavada and
it is rooted in the external sets of
norms and circumstances and and duties
that you've taken on
it's on the same level
so by assuming that you should you have
right and it must be done the doubt must
be get rid of you then adopt external
set of behavior almost magically a
magical connection if i don't do this oh
because i did this this is what happened
all rooted in simply not acknowledging
that the pain needs to be endured first
and that brings me to another little
point i want to mention so the first
three factors
they're together
like you could maybe theoretically kind
of differentiate what comes first but
overall they arise together they exist
together in that sense
so it wouldn't be one leads to the other
that leads to the third one they're just
there because they're kind of three
aspects of the same externally projected
attitude and that is in common to all
three the external assumption of yourself as
the external assumption of yourself as
in yourself exists independent of this
experience as a whole
uh the external uh dependence on the
sets of norms behaviors authorities
not because you chose to do so and then
feeling the weight and the uncertainty
of your choice
and of course the external engagement in
order to prevent the pain of doubt
so if you start uprooting this external
assumption on any of these three hindrances the
on any of these three hindrances the
other twos will be uprooted as well uh
fetters sorry the other two will be
uprooted as well
so there will be the difference between
somebody who is experiencing doubt
without being fettered by it and
somebody who's fat abide
so the one
who is not fatter by it means he has
endured it long enough
so that his mind has come down within
that kicking and screaming of trying to
get rid of the existential doubt that's
the most unpleasant thing
and once it comes down within kicking a
screen by not acting out of it
you then get to see it as an enduring
phenomenon so as unpleasant as it is you see it
so as unpleasant as it is you see it
that it has arisen and thus he has to
cease and your clarification of it engagement
and your clarification of it engagement
seeking the answer just to get rid of
the pain of it would just be to cover up
and you know that so you won't be fatter
by it you still be pressured by it hence
the hindrance of doubt
so you still need to train your mind on
more subtler levels to not act out to
not welcome and so on but you're not
fatter because you cannot
adopt that view again
putting you're getting rid of the pain
first as a valuable as a valid thing and
thinking doubt just came externally and
if i address it no you realize no any
direction of my effort towards external
circumstances in order to deal with the
doubt cannot be conceived anymore because you
cannot be conceived anymore because you
you understood that you see the doubt
doesn't come from the external world
so why would you be addressing it there
and people who have been addressing it
there is the one who haven't seen where
it came from because they haven't
endured it long enough
so and that kind of
comes back to you know i must i'm sure
we said it before
the whole like
sota party and the three factors yes you
need to know
you know what the buddha thought what
you know clarify what the where the
feathers are what the
and so on but fundamentally people don't
get the right view not because they
don't have the enough information and
utterance of another
in terms of what the right view is they
don't get it because they haven't
endured things sufficiently long enough
on that
level that's that's usually taken for
granted this must be avoided must be
prevented must be managed must be
covered up must be dealt with
and that's why they as we said before
that's why the only summary is not
developed things are not endured
rightly on the right level
now here's a question suppose somebody
wants to deliberately move towards that
feather of doubt by keeping the question
who am i alive and making that as the
main practice is that a valid approach
it could be it depends on what other
things that person does
do they do that
cultivation of that attitude paired with
with sense restraint
guiding of the sense those
um not acting out towards other
hindrances as well
and then keep themselves in question
then yeah then it would probably be like
one of those ways that they were
described as
quick and unpleasant
but they also seen
in certain discourses as as questions
not to be pursued like am i am i not who
am i answer on well no see
not to be pursued if you still have a
view that the answer will resolve the
question yeah so that's the difference
between dealing with this you are not
seeking for the answer you just want to
cultivate the question exactly so that
it reveals the underlying pain you're
trying to get rid of
and endure it
because i mean
am i liable to
future unwholesome states
that's a question that's a valid
question yeah exactly
uh
many other questions that would evolve
even around the artavada and so on would
be valid questions if you are not
as i said seeking the answer to get rid
of the discomfort of it so if you're
asking a question for the sake of
cultivating the attitude yeah that's
that's the whole practice of you know
why am i doing what i'm doing um whether
my intentions are rooted it's all it all
begins with a question and stays within
the question
but the difference is whether you can
bear it
to stay on the level of the question
without giving into the temptation of
but if i just get the clarification just
get the answer
then everything is going to be fine then
things will fall into place and then
abnormal practice is to not overshoot it
and not ignore it i undershoot it
and yeah that practice begins with that
uncertainty of your own
questionable existence that's the whole
point and that's exactly why people would
and that's exactly why people would
become dependent on external
circumstances in terms of virtue
uh getting rid of doubt even in terms of
your own view of yourself
it's because you overshot the mark for
so long so many times you develop that
became a threshold now
of of what what is as i said before
so that's like whenever i said it's not
about uh finding answer to these existential
uh finding answer to these existential
questions it's about becoming the
existential questions
so in during them
until you get used to it then the pain
of the existential questioning will go
away because it was only conditioned by
your wanting to get rid of it
but the question remained and then you
realize well the question the question
of this existence is the nature of
existence it's uncertain
cannot be answered in those positive
terms that you are used to operating on
account of your existence
so that's so like you know uh existence
precedes the essence
it just has to be that way
so another slightly related but somewhat
different question we spoke about before
i thought now we can actually so what's
the difference then
or rather no what comes first
hindrances or fetters um
um
because you were saying
uh
there's this fundamental wrong view
that um
the the the feta
of doubt implies
and by uprooting that or by by seeing
that that wrong view one still is liable
to hindrance but
but not to the full extent yeah of the
feta yeah yeah exactly
the hindrances are on a practical level
more fundamental
it's by not having a mind developed in
regard to hindrances all these
factors exist
exist
that fatter you
and the reason why i bring this up
because it is quite commonly assumed
other way around whereby you think these
factors are like these mystical things
they will fall off when you have these
deep insights of your samadhi or
whatever and hindrances are kind of come and go
and hindrances are kind of come and go
and as long as you're not lustful or
angry or doubtful you're free from them
actually you're not liability is
discovered in other talks liability to
hindrances so liability to last arising means
so liability to last arising means
you're still within the domain of lust
you have not surmounted them
thus if you surmount one of them
properly you smarted all five and that's
the first jana
because people do and i heard even like
teachings being sort of taught by saying
well no you just look
um like in terms of last for example
like most of the time you're not lustful
thus your practice is going well it's
like no that's not the measure
i mean a person in coma is most of the
time not lost for
because he's unconscious does that mean
he's going towards enlightenment no
so you can be most of the time not
lustful or angry but
could last arise
if you're uncertain in regard to that
means you're well within the domain of
lust domain of the hindrances
because by same logic then you could say
well most of the time you're not
engaging in a sexual intercourse and
when you do even such engagement doesn't
last as long as most of the time when
you're not engaging that's most of the
time you're celibate
but that's not how celibacy works most
of the time you don't kill anybody and
if you were to kill somebody it would
last for a second only
so most of the time you're you're
keeping the precepts of not killing no
it doesn't matter could i kill somebody
could i engage in sensuality yes
that's it
your mind is then within the hindrances
so most of the time you shouldn't be
doing it and while you're not doing it
you should then start looking at the
liability of doing or could i do it yes
that is a problem
there is no safety there
but if we measure
whether there is a problem not by the
duration of how long you do it well
you can get away with everything then
because you know most of those things
wouldn't last
as long as you know not doing those
things
say you have never heard about a
buddhist teaching
but for whatever reason or through whatever
for whatever reason or through whatever
teaching you are actually practicing
towards freedom from the liability to
fight hindrances
not just whether they're actually
present or not you are surmounting them
as a whole
in other words you're developing the
ghana yes
then in your case
in your case
without any instruction of the buddhist
teaching even the first three factors let's say
even the first three factors let's say
like that and won't be as flattering
because the mind is not fueling them
anymore through wrong attitude and
acting out of hindrances
and that's exactly
how in the suttas
some monks or people or like even
followers of other trade
practices met the buddha heard one sentence and
met the buddha heard one sentence and
became like boom sothephanazanagam is
instantaneously yes it's because the mind has been
yes it's because the mind has been
developed beforehand thoroughly they
just needed somebody to put the pieces
together pieces that they have
cultivated and and
and developed
and formed
yeah the buddha after his awakening
considered who would be the first ones
to understand
which i have discovered
and it was his two teachers who actually
taught him neither perception nor
perception and the base of nothingness
exactly yeah the other way so imagine
imagine if the first just
measly first jhana surmounts all the
hindrances and and outside it develops
the mind to that extent
imagine how much more the mind of
somebody who has developed neither
perception or perception outside of the
buddhist teaching i mean as the buddhist
himself said oh it's such a great loss
for them that they died before they
heard my teaching because they virtually
had no dust in their eyes they were so
close yeah they would have seen this
very quickly they would have probably
not even finished the sentence they
would have known exactly what he's
talking about
because the work has been done
so that's why even throughout the day if
you are
surmounting the hindrances by not acting
out by enduring
by recognizing the present
liability of hindrances
so see they are not directly present so
you could say oh last is absent
anger is absent but it is present as a
possibility and you need to start to see
that and endure that
you are actually practicing towards
janna even if you don't sit crossed like
then watch your nostrils
well especially if you don't cross leg
and watch your nostrils
yes but you see the possibility of
something means that one needs to become
sensitive to the let's say negative
aspect of experience something isn't
happening but could be happening exactly
and how does one become sensitive to
that do you become sensitive to that by
do you become sensitive to that by
practicing sensitivity of bodily
sensations and concentration
could you let's say that could you
become sensitive to that by doing
meditation techniques and focusing
practices
but that wouldn't be
um
that wouldn't be the main thing that
makes that happen so basically no
exactly yeah
because you know
any such practices we just established
is on the level of attending to objects
which means all you're going to be
training yourself is is attending to
more specific objects within objects and
this is not in that level that's right
so first you need to be able to endure
it so that's how you will become more
sensitive to those things to those
liabilities by not acting out by enduring by not
by not acting out by enduring by not
trying to get rid of the discomfort of
pressure to act out by by enduring it
and not acting up so not covering it up
and not acting out
the result is oh you're going to become
very sensitive
you're going to see it even before you
feel it
so now you're very discerning of it and
that's that's exactly the practice
and this is
also how dwelling bodily secluded not
having other people around that give a
sort of confirmation like i exist i'm
this way that way and someone to not
talk much because most of the time
talking also has this sort of let us say
interpersonal domain of wanting to be
acknowledged something to be understood
and so on this can easily feed into this
whole assumption of self and this is
what i am and this is how i'm seen so
when you just get out of that situation
it's it well not necessarily by itself
but it certainly moves into the
direction of having this sort of
background uncertainty
around your existence becoming more
salient put a sense restraint on top of
that and the whole situation basically begins
and the whole situation basically begins
to sort of cook and boil a bit
without needing to make any effort
positively in order to get somewhere
exactly this becomes the positive effort exactly
this becomes the positive effort exactly
which is basically negative yeah exactly
so like protecting the certain
circumstances recognizing what it would
be detrimental and then avoiding it
before you do it that's your inverted
become a positive effort exactly yes
um but is from the point of view of
what's usually assumed to be the
positive effort of practice yeah this is
a negative method of practice yeah and
this is stuff you don't do so that your
practice arises as a result of it yeah
and then the inadvertent situation of
that would be to sit with a group of
people focusing on the tip of your nose
yeah exactly it's a very much specific
thing you do yeah
and and just generally the um even say
even if you're not
engaging with other with company just
and if you're like you know if you're
free from matava then so on so there is
no perpetuation of such
assumptions and validations and so on
still engaging with others talking
company is distracting on its
own yes it takes away the mind from
itself even in neutral terms even if
it's a neutral type of engagement
so that's why solitude is necessary
physical solitude is necessary
one would think
being among people could be a good
exercise to
be able to control not control but to
able to
deal with these things
i mean well that's the whole point
you're not supposed to deal with them
you're supposed to uproot them
it's not about learning how to deal
if yes if you want to learn how to deal
being with people you know getting a
psychotherapy degree all of that is
probably going to be helpful your
management but dharma is not a management it's
but dharma is not a management it's
uprooting
so that's the question you should ask
yourself do i want to deal with these
things or do i just want to approve them
once and for all
and then more drastic measures need to
be taken such as
not relying on people and not relying on
learning the skill of management because
that requires to be affected first
but one could say okay i'm secluded and
i don't talk to anybody and now
i see
it
appears that
you know i have
i'm not acting out i mean it
if you are with other people you can uh
they can do something you could
right well see that's the problem there
is that you can't see whether you're
liable to greet a virgin delusion
without external help
and circumstances prodding you and
pushing you which means you have not
developed what needs to be developed
so yes
circumstances can remind you of these
things but if you need circumstances to
remind you means you are not seeing the
liability that doesn't need
circumstances that's the whole point
you are liable to be affected by things
when you are not being affected by them
directly but if the only way for you to recognize
but if the only way for you to recognize
that you're liable is to be affected in
the first place means proof
more work and sense restraint will be
required because again that's the level
you need to really transcend and get
beyond so you want to be secluded and it will
so you want to be secluded and it will
enough it should be enough for you to
just ask yourself
can the lust arise
and if you are unclear that's enough for
you to know that yes i am liable
and then you train in regard to that
question and in regard to that liability
not oh i don't know thus let me go and
seek the external last to confirm that i
could the fact is that you don't know
means yes that's the answer you can be
affected because you don't know whether
you can or cannot be affected
and for that person
being prompted by other yeah sure
somebody buddha can come and out of
compassion tell you something more and
then kind of make you think better and
so on
but the way well at least the way i
the way well at least the way i
understood what you said initially was
being with others is good because it
will remind you of great diversion
delusion in the work you need to do now
it will remind you of acute greed
aversion delusion
and the only reason that's possible is
because you're already not seeing the
liability of those things
of those things
and for that
seclusion is necessary
that's quite a common view though people
saying like okay i'm living together
with someone yeah of course we are
occasionally pushing one another's not
pushing one another's buttons all of
this is unpresent
i have to deal with it and
that's the practice yeah exactly but
even then you know having your buttons
pressed if you are half reasonable you
might develop some patience or endurance
but it is all within the domain of
sensuality stuff well again and even if
you don't have anybody pressing your
buttons if you're honest with yourself
you could recognize that my buttons
could be pressed and that's enough for
somebody who has developed the mind
sufficiently to begin practicing that
but that's almost they could be pressed
means that's it that is a form of
pressed yes i don't need others external
again we come back to that requiring
that certain assumed threshold of what
is
so an actual last diversion illusion is
what last diversion delusion is
the only way to deal with liability
uh with possibility of last diversion
illusion is to actively engage with last
diversion delusion no no it's other way
around you need to stop engaging so to see
you need to stop engaging so to see
liability correctly and then you will
have no need to engage
exactly
and there is a difference there
that we can now obviously differentiate
like are you paired
with another person in a sense of a
teacher who is not pushing your buttons in terms
who is not pushing your buttons in terms
of last diversion delusion but giving
you instruction necessary for practice
or are you just paired with random
strangers that you're just clashing with
emotionally and so on due to
circumstances history or whatever else
those are two very different you can say
well see both the company but they're
very different types of company
and that's exactly what what was it the
rhinoceros says yeah
don't seek company just with anyone only
with equal or better than yourself
and even then it's for the purpose of
learning if it's not for that purpose that
if it's not for that purpose that
company should not be cultivated now you
might be stuck in certain companies
which you have to endure
but if you now start justifying that for
your practice that's that's a cover you
want that's a cover-up yeah
yeah say more better in terms of virtue
composure and understanding and the
views yes exactly same or better equal
or higher yeah
now obviously as i said
where you're gonna find that today like
how many people would seek that
so you need to recognize okay the the
circumstance i mean are not the most
favorable but let me at least not cover them up
but let me at least not cover them up
uh and due to discomfort of it and that
might make rise to some other choices
that i have not considered they might be
beneficial for my practice but those
choices will not arise if you try to
justify your circumstance cover them up
and kind of ignore what you know need to
be done such as yeah sense restraint
guarding the sense though seclusion
not engagement
solitude discerning these liabilities
and so on
yeah non-distraction so
so
do i spend how do i spend my time
throughout the day am i engaging for the
sake of company
for the sake of distraction
for the sake of boredom
again household or not it applies the
same it's the same rooted motivation
where is it rooted in
and then you might recognize well it's a
bit too much to do this right away
but you mustn't cover it up okay it's
too much to do right away i must make
myself able to do it
eventually later on not like oh it's too
much now i can afford to not think about
it yet at the same time entertain this
notion that you are still practicing
yeah and then that can also be the view
that practice and study is about in that
sense gaining or accumulating something
whereas actually it's about abandoning
things it's about undoing yeah it's
about doing everything about undoing
rather than adding some rather than
keeping what is already going on and
then adding something to it
some sort of
spiritual layer to your life let's say
yeah whereas actually it's about taking
whereas actually it's about taking
things away from what you are already
doing which then will
create more favorable circumstances and
a sort of space to to see what's the
next step
experientially how would you take away
how would you take away
maybe somebody else can join i don't
know how would you take away
those things that you know you need to
take away
like what you just said
well first of all by seeing the danger
in in perpetuating those things what
would those things be
in broad terms well um this is obviously
the whole domain of sensuality
centrality would be one of them yeah
well that would be the main one and and
all because you see we can say sensuality
because you see we can say sensuality
but it might not be clear
what actually encompasses this whole
domain of sensuality that that's now
another question it's easy to to keep
coming back to this point but um to just
see where sensuality begins and ends so
to speak already implies that yeah
sexually that could be separate though
yes because in a sense that whole domain
needs to have ceased in order for you to
have the direct knowledge what is the
extent of the domain yeah so so
but it's not going to be somebody who
doesn't know the extent of their domain
but they want to start
uh
undoing things as we said
okay of course you know you take on the
precepts yes
god descends those
where else do you look for the undoing
where would you find internally what you
need to undo
even if you don't have any specific
information you need to undo this or
this or this there's a certain thing you
can find that's
uniformly present in everything that you
need to undo yeah it's a basic
self-forgetfulness like like when somebody is doing
like like when somebody is doing
something whether it is going to a
restaurant being absorbed in food
unpleasant circumstances
binge watching television series and so
on what is pleasant about that is is the
unawareness of existence and the burden
that comes with it what is in common to
eating in the restaurant
pleasure of distraction pleasure
forgetfulness what is the the uncon what is the common
what is the the uncon what is the common
trait
it's not distractions dearness sorry
dearness that's yeah so what's what like
things that are dead to you why are they
dead to you
anything that's there that you regard as
friendly including your own mind is that
you should see it as an enemy as an
assassin why are you regarding it as dear and
why are you regarding it as dear and
friendly
you don't see the danger
and when something is not dangerous
how is it felt present
safe it's that safety which of course it
felt pleasant
so
any safety you find in anything you can
stand out of mind in that
and that would be different things
that's why there is no external set
of predetermined steps and motions that
it will apply to all of us
some people will find safety in doing
certain things in certain habits instead
access to certain things some people
will find something else what is in
common is you do find a sense of safety
in it in something in something in doing
something in having something in
belonging to something
so if you follow the thread of where you
find safety and keep pulling it out yeah
you are going in the right direction
because then there will be nothing that
you find safe in this world and that's
the true disenchantment and this passion
that will result in our handshake
but see in order to do that you need to
be able to endure such lack of safety
without losing your mind or or breaking
down or distracting yourself
yeah but we're talking about safety here
in the context of one's existence we're
not talking about whether you put on
your safety belt in the car or not yes
no no but i'm not saying like don't put
on your seat belt in the car oh right
right no no no no no no no no see
i'm doing the sense of the thread of
what where you find safety and does not
mean exposing yourself to danger exactly
that's my point yes no quite the
opposite yes so
you don't need to go external uh extreme
circumstances you just recognize
there are things see because you are not
an arahant means you are resting upon
something upon some possession some
value some ideas
either way you are finding safety in
them to that extent you feel sheltered
stop questioning that stop putting that
in question undermining it and there it
is the most acute practice you can have
if you can hold it
that's actually one of the four
summaries of the dhamma that you know
this world is without shelter and
protection it literally says that
it literally says that
oh yeah exactly through and through yeah
like there's nothing and it's it's
similar in other studies he realized
there is nothing worth
holding on possessing clinging to
whatever you want to translate it yes
because to that extent you'll be
undermined by it
and that was what you were telling the
other day that
that renunciation is uh getting out of
the security like even even if you don't
necessarily see all these like nuances
if you start keeping the precepts like
rightly not just on a level of external
authority but because you choose to do
so and you keep choosing to do so every
single time yeah that renunciation is
emulating that
the the basically uh that undermining of
things that you're taking for granted
that giving up their relinquishment
and renunciating the household life is
even more and
getting out of your security and
exactly yeah because
see sometimes people can renounce
immediate things that provide you with
safety but they cannot renounce
the need
for maybe
access to safety so i'm not accessing it
now but i would like to have an option
to access it if i need to
so to that extent you are still not not
truly putting yourself in that position
of
uncertainty so it's like okay yeah i'm not engaging
so it's like okay yeah i'm not engaging
with this but if push comes to shove i
could and that in itself will offer you
safety the possibility that you could
engage with things that
you used to engage with for the sake of
safety and relief and pleasure and so on
that's enough that becomes then your
safety your relief your pleasure i'm not
doing it but i would if i'm pressed far
enough and that's something you actually need
and that's something you actually need
to abandon
you need to give up and just just decide
no i won't even if my life depends on it
i want to engage with it
and then it feels very differently it's
kind of similar to what we spoke before
like in terms of centrality and giving
up the addiction
try to give up cigarettes or similar
and then it's like oh yes i'm not i'm
not smoking currently
but if the need comes up
i could
and they're fine with that idea there's
like no you shouldn't be fine with it so
you should even decide on the level of
if a need comes up no never again
and then it feels very different then
the weight is much more serious
and the widow gave the similar similar
suture that the simile of the quail
he says sometimes i make a little
little rule and say monks don't do that
but it's a little it's insignificant and
then someone say well that's
insignificant so they do it
then some other monks say well that's
insignificant so they make the effort
and abandon it because it's
insignificant why would you then do it
and the girl said the monks that
it's truly insignificant
but the ones that don't abandon it
they're like a quail
that's tied down with insignificant
rotten half rotten ropes but because
it's a weak quail those such ropes are
enough to keep it bound
the ones that abandoned
even the seemingly insignificant things
are basically like elephants tied with
leather straps but they would because
they're elephants they would break the
leather straps so in other words things
feel insignificant because you're not
abandoning them
if you mastered the determination to say
no in the ultimate sense you realize
there are leather straps actually
but it's easy to cut oh no this is just
a rope it's just a rotten rope this is
not a bond
because you're not committing to
abandoning it that would mean it will be
felt differently
if you decide in that ultimate sense
never again
then you feel the weight then you oh
it's an actual strap a leather strap but
because you have decided such thing and
abstain from such actions you become an
elephant that can break even the leather
straps
yes so by abandoning that possibility
of coming back to it in the future
all the
all the weight is let us say
concentrated in the present which is why
the burden is fully felt yeah
burden of the entire extent exactly all
the future possible it doesn't matter
now it's it's it's the same
determination covering it all never
again yes but when that possibility is
there like i might come back to it in
the future this is it that's a relief
yeah precisely so the burden in the present
precisely so the burden in the present
is not felt because there is this sort
of time interval like in the future
somewhere somewhere
this could still exist for me and
consequently the problem is not seen now
they say you give up sensuality
i'll never
use sensuality as a distraction or
escape from the pain
i feel the agitation i feel so i won't
ever go in that direction again
ever and then you feel them now what do i
and then you feel them now what do i
yeah this
well i don't know what to do i don't
know what to do now
but i don't know what i will not do
so then you have to endure it exactly
and do that lack of safety but not
compromise the direction you know you
shouldn't go
and once you do it long enough
you get to see where to go and what to
do and if there is anything you need to
do yes so this is this negative approach
again it's not about finding something
positively to move towards it's about
abandoning that future
possibility and not sustaining that yeah
that's future possibility so you get to
see the dharma if you basically remove
all of your attitudes views preconceived
notions that are covering it up
even the buddha himself
that's the only way you can do it he
said oh it's like finding the ancient
path there was covered and i uncovered
it
but you don't get to see the dhamma by
doing practices on top of everything
else all the views and notions and
preconceived ideas
no that's just piling up piling up
piling up piling up or wrong views
if those things are not seen as a result
of undoing all of your views notions
habits and so on
it's it's going to be on the level of
wrong practice
because any viewer that one holds
root in this sense of safety basically
yes yeah and then the right view begins
by recognizing that the right practice
is about undoing all of your safety
stances internally so that's still technically a
internally so that's still technically a
view
but it's a view that actually undermines
need for views
and that's when arahant eventually when
it becomes another hunt is
gone beyond the views
so even the right view is gone in him so
to speak
ceased no need for it anymore
because the views have been extinguished
and that's where the views are
standpoints of safety
yeah we touched on that last time that's
right when we do what we wanted to speak
about it again the safety the pleasure
that comes from views of why you hold on
to your videos
you abandon sensuality
essential pleasures yeah yeah yeah and then you
pleasures yeah yeah yeah and then you
start holding on to the safety of the
views yeah yeah yeah very much yeah this
is the conviction the certainty
yeah it protects it from pain
protection lots of people double down in
these views once they and their suitors
say that once summoners and brahms
withdrawn from sensuality then they
started hearing i
doubling down even harder to the views
and again views not on the level of
these metaphysical ideas of cosmos no
views on the level of
you shouldn't be sitting like that and
he shouldn't be speaking like that or
how can he do this how can they do that
those are the views
all of those are the views and that's
exactly what summoners and brahmanas
fall out over
you know they live keeping the same
rules same same environment and then they
same same environment and then they
absolutely kind of
the minds lose perspective on account of
just these stance standpoints because i
find it
comforting and find sense of safety if
things are done this way
that's my view
and if i take that view for granted now
i will require other people to do things
that way because i am being compromised
by others not following these external
sets of circumstances that i established
upon my safety upon now would you say
that that is feature of
exactly that's exactly what it's
yeah that's why like it's not enough for
you to just be virtuous to approve the
factor of syllabato para mas exactly the
view of management as we said before
that's why it fetches you
yeah but where is the actual safe place
well it's exactly that abandoning any
need for safety having nothing to
protect relinquishing anything that
would require protection
means then you're safe because nothing
can be threatened yeah as reflecting on
sickness that is the example fundamental
sickness aging death yes that's
fundamental undermining seeing sickness
as a possibility is gonna cut through
all the safety and comfort of having a
house having something to eat sensual
pleasures clothing all of that suddenly
loses perspective if this body can
basically break apart and you have to
experience on your own that's a good
example so how would you then
sustain such
such
like say a householder
or a monk
you might get a spur of you know
contemplating sickness that cuts to your
sense of safety but then it fades away
then you lose that edge how would you
sustain that edge
well this is um going towards the
direction of right recollection what is
it that you're actually bringing to mind
and the more the mind well it's the same
things you recollected before you're
doing the same recollections but there
is no more edge to it
why is that
well either because the work has all
been done
or
well that there can be a tendency that
just thinking about something is the
same as enduring the actual uncertainty
which it is not
the presence of a thought need not be
but why would that happen
like something you've endured now it
just went into you just thinking about
it and it's not felt anymore because
what started out as an authentic
practice gradually
becomes a way of finding safety sure but
why
it's removed from
the situation my presence
well or because so why would you lose a
sense of urgency say you're thinking the
same thing
there was a sense of urgency
but then it fades away even when you
really try to to get it back what a
craving comes in to use all of that to
avoid to ward off unpleasant feeling so it
to ward off unpleasant feeling so it
transforms into a management technique
again which is missing the point
it could be
you're putting it in front of you like
it could be but why would you be doing
all of that
that's the real
so it's like say as i said
you start contemplating sickness that
comes through cuts through the sense of
safety and you feel that
and you feel that
and you're very alert as a result of it
but then it fades away
did you do something wrong or it just
happens on its own or
how can you then get that sense of
urgency back
that the edge is gone why does the edge
go away why can't you just sustain that
edge up until you're in another hunt
why did the buddha have to remind even
uh
sekkas the the noble disciples did they
still have work to do why would then
they be why do people why does the mind
become complacent
so that's really
the question here
any ideas
why does the mind become complacent even
like you know you're clear so it's not
on the level of well i think i know what
sickness you know you actually know what
sickness is it cuts through
possessions and safety
but then you still become complacent
does that
complacency do you ever say in it do you do anything
do you ever say in it do you do anything
that results in it
it just happens
you you come back to your safety that
you are not in that moment well you can
come back to it in your mind but you
don't feel that edge anymore
so why is that why is it covered up
you're not seeing it
that's obvious
you won't be seeing it because it's
covered up so why is it why are you not
seeing him why is he covered up
we actually we actually uh answered it
before that
not hinders us well no when we said
about well yes sure but then when we
said about the whole practice is about
uncovering things
so if things get covered up such as this
edge gets covered up means
your circumstances your choices
that you make need to be upgraded need
to change
so you cannot directly access that edge
anymore because it was covered up by what well
because it was covered up by what well
by lack of seclusion
by company
by distraction
by still choosing three diversion
delusion on some level of action
so you you start i mean if you start
thinking like this you can get then you
if if the edge disappears you use that
as a symptom so you don't just try to oh
let me just contemplate and revoke that
novelty of that that edge of sickness
no no
i can't do that it will be covered up
why so am i liable to covering up the sense
so am i liable to covering up the sense
of urgency that can be another line of
reasoning you can use
similar to other lines of reasoning in
the suit as they would encourage
so and and that's my point so it doesn't
get covered up on its own it will it
will disappear the edge either because
you're an arahant exactly as you said
or because
your choices and actions and
circumstances that you've been
tolerating on certain levels are
resulting in accumulation that covers it
up
so even that contemplation of sickness
needs to be seen in a wider context and
if this edge goes off then then rather
than there are only two reasons
yeah sure he won't be on the level of a
protogenous cover up when he just
ignores and so on
but if the edge is gone
if that uncertainty the background to
the very start of this long talk
when you were existing as a question
you know the pain of that can disappear
if you practice rightly but the question
remains because the nature remains
and it's that on each other then
prevents you to commit to find safety in
things that are uncertain find ownership
in things that are uncertain
so
the discomfort of that question the
sense of urgency of that question will
disappear if you're either in arahant or
if you cover it up
and that's exactly why the buddha needed
to encourage even sekkas who would
become complacent
so you can keep asking what happened i
abandoned well exactly just ask yourself
do i feel the sense of urgency no oh is
it because i'm an arahant
well if the answer to that is no
then it's because i'm covering it up and
you should start feeling urgency in
regard to that
and how do i cover it up is it just an
how do i cover it up is it just an
accident accidental cover-up no
how am i spending my day what are the
choices i'm making throughout the day
what am i staying to my that's how i'm
covering it up so it's always
intentional choices
if these
mistakes obstructions cannot happen
accidentally that's my whole point
and practically speaking it's going to
come down to okay so am i secluded
enough is most of my daily time spent in
is most of my daily time spent in
company in work
in talking
in thinking things that are secondary
or do i actually
try and protect that
so that indirectly
i protect the context of the sense of
urgency being covered up
those all the obstacles for the sega the
lighting inverter exactly the lighting
works sleeping a lot talking sleeping
yeah
but even for a non-seka who wants to as
i said start to do things rightly you
need that sense of urgency because you
know you can think about it when there
is no distraction when you're alone but
then you get your duties with speaking
we're doing this we're doing that
and you kind of forget or you don't feel
the question mark anymore you know it's
there theoretically abstractly you'll
give the same amount but you don't feel
it the same way that's seclusion you're
not putting yourself in a dangerous
position exactly
and that's a seclusion is necessary
company distraction obviously centrality
acting out of ill will and so on
this precisely the buddha says
or asked ananda
to
instruct like those who have newly gone
forth this is five things uh to patimoca
this is five things uh to patimoca
then secondly uh sense restraint uh
don't talk much
develop bodily secluded and work on the
right view yeah those are the five
things for anyone who has left the
household life and goes forth so just to
do that regardless of any methods or
techniques to put yourself in that
situation and then not come to morning and evening
and then not come to morning and evening
meetings but just go and pin apart and
have the party mocha every fortnight and
other than that you are on your own
is gonna
well it seems to me well this is going
to expose everything that we just talked
about so then the question comes down to how
so then the question comes down to how
do you prevent sorry the answer comes
down to
to the question of how do you prevent
uh losing the edge of the sense of
urgency is like
start sort of you know
reflecting upon and and broadening
your questioning and context so to find
all the indirect things that you are
still doing
that eventually accumulate and cover up
the edge of the sense of urgency so it's
not felt
so yeah i keep the precepts of this but
i don't feel it anymore well okay so are
you sufficiently secluded
are you sufficiently withdrawn how about
your mental states
do they still revolve around greedover
all these little things that are not as
bad obviously as before
now are bad enough yeah to cover up
so now you have to remove the finer ones
but now they are the impurities now
they're the only impurities that thus
they are the ones that are covering it
up now yeah
and that can be done once the coarse
stuff is sort of exactly so
restrained by body by speech by patty
mocha by precepts sense restrained
guiding of the sense those sure
but that was just the beginning
that was just the beginning
so if the sense of urgency if the edge
if the question mark is not felt anymore
means now there is a time for a
next layer of removal of the cover up
yes